<?xml version="1.0"?>
<courseleaf>



<text>
<![CDATA[  
<h2>Overview</h2>
<p>The Graduate Group in Health and Medical Sciences offers a five-year program leading to a Master of Science (MS) degree in Health and Medical Sciences from UC Berkeley and a Medical Doctorate (MD) from UCSF. The program’s mission is to produce academic and community leaders in American medicine through early exposure to public health disciplines, medical humanities, bioethics, and social and behavioral sciences. <span class="s1">UC Berkeley awards the master’s degree upon successful completion of the first </span><span class="s2"> 2.5 years</span><span class="s1"> of work, and UCSF awards the medical degree after successful completion of the </span><span class="s2">remaining 2.5 years</span><span class="s1"> years.</span></p>
<h3>Undergraduate Program</h3>
<p>There is no undergraduate program in Health and Medical Sciences.</p>
<h3>Graduate Program</h3>
<p><a href="/archive/2016-17/graduate/degree-programs/health-medical-sciences-program/">Health and Medical Sciences</a>
: Joint MS/MD (in cooperation with UCSF)</p>

  
]]>
</text>
<faculty>
<![CDATA[
<h2>Faculty and Instructors</h2><p class="facitem"><strong>+ </strong>Indicates this faculty member is the recipient of the Distinguished Teaching Award.</p><h4>Faculty</h4><p class="facitem"><strong>John R. Balmes, <i>Professor in Residence</i>. </strong></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Lisa F. Barcellos, <i>Associate Professor</i>. </strong>Public health, genetic epidemiology, human genetics, autoimmune diseases, multiple schlerosis, lupus erythematosus, rheumatoid arthritis, epigenetics, genomics, computational biology.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/14591"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Jack Colford, <i>Professor</i>. </strong>Public health, epidemiology, infectious diseases, biostatistics, meta-analysis.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/14621"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Laurent Coscoy, <i>Associate Professor</i>. </strong>Immunology, viruses, viral infection, immune responses, immune evasion.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/13882"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Ronald Dahl, <i>Professor</i>. </strong>Decision-making, adolescence, brain development, behavioral and emotional health, pubertal maturation, affective neuroscience, social neuroscience.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/15013"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>William H. Dow, <i>Professor</i>. </strong>Health economics, international health, economic demography.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/14634"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Lia C. Fernald, <i>Associate Professor</i>. </strong>Poverty, obesity, child development, public health nutrition, global health, psychosocial and biological determinants of health, overweight, nutritional and epidemiologic transition, chronic disease, malnutrition, child health and development, early experience, inequality and health disparities, Latino health, Mexican-Americans and other immigrant groups, stress hormones, salivary cortisol.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/14293"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Mary K. Firestone, <i>Professor</i>. </strong>Soils, environmental policy, environmental science, policy &amp; management, wildlife, miicrobial biology.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/14669"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Sylvia Guendelman, <i>Professor</i>. </strong>Public health, maternal &amp; child health, health and social behavior, health policy and management, specialty area in multicultural health.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/14756"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Helen Halpin, <i>Professor</i>. </strong>Public health, health policy and management, health services &amp; policy analysis.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/14780"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>S. Katharine Hammond, <i>Professor</i>. </strong>Public health, environmental health sciences.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/14782"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Seth M. Holmes, <i>Assistant Professor</i>. </strong>Immigration and migration, medical anthropology with foci on social theory and ethnography, social studies of medicine and science, social difference related to race, social difference related to socioeconomic status, social difference related to citizenship, social difference related to gender, social difference related to sexuality, the naturalization and normalization of social hierarchies and health disparities, social suffering and symbolic violence, urban and rural Latin America and North America, population health with focus on global health, population health with focus on health disparities, population health with focus on social determinants of health.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/14857"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Alan Hubbard, <i>Associate Professor</i>. </strong></p><p class="facitem"><strong>William J. Jagust, <i>Professor</i>. </strong>Neuroscience, cognition, brain aging, dementia, imaging, Alzheimer&amp;amp;#039;s disease.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/14887"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Thomas W. Laqueur, <i>Professor</i>. </strong>Medicine, religion, body, human rights.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/16794"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Jane Mauldon, <i>Associate Professor</i>. </strong>Demography, public policy, quantitative methods, health policy and economics, poverty and public policy, the teen-parent component of California_Â _s welfare reforms.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/15096"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Maria Mavroudi, <i>Professor</i>. </strong>Byzantine studies.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/14106"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Guy Micco, <i>Clinical Professor</i>. </strong>Aging/old age, suffering, and death, the medical humanities.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/15114"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Suellen Miller, <i>Adjunct Professor</i>. </strong></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Mahasin S. Mujahid, <i>Assistant Professor</i>. </strong></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Amani M. Nuru-Jeter, <i>Associate Professor</i>. </strong>Health disparities, race/ethnicity, socioeconomic position, stress and health, place and health, cardiovascular risk, birth outcomes.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/15031"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Lee Riley, <i>Professor</i>. </strong>Public health, infectious diseases, molecular epidemiology, global health, tuberculosis, drug-resistant infections, slum health.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/15036"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>George W. Rutherford, <i>Adjunct Professor</i>. </strong></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Allan H. Smith, <i>Professor</i>. </strong>Public health, epidemiology, biostatistics, environmental health sciences.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/15042"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Sandra Smith, <i>Associate Professor</i>. </strong>Trust, urban poverty, joblessness, race and ethnic inequality, social capital and social networks.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/15466"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Harvey M. Weinstein, <i>Clinical Professor</i>. </strong></p><h4>Lecturers</h4><p class="facitem"><strong>Karen Sokal-Gutierrez, <i>Lecturer</i>. </strong>Nutrition, maternal-child health, early childhood health, oral health, child health in developing countries, children&amp;amp;#039;s health in child care, parenting education, health education for low literacy populations, health disparities.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/15045"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><h4>Emeritus Faculty</h4><p class="facitem"><strong>+ Marian C. Diamond, <i>Professor Emeritus</i>. </strong>Environment, neuroanatomy, immune functions, hormones, mammalian forebrain structures, Cambodian orphanage, cerebral neocortex.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/14152"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Sharon E. Fleming, <i>Professor Emeritus</i>. </strong>Plant biology, health and nutrition.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/14674"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Joyce C. Lashof, <i>Professor Emeritus</i>. </strong>Public health, health policy.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/14030"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Meredith Minkler, <i>Professor Emerita</i>. </strong>Public health, health and social behavior, community health education.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/15128"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>Eleanor Rosch, <i>Professor Emeritus</i>. </strong>Cognition, psychology, concepts, Eastern psychologies, psychologies of religion, cross cultural, causality.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/15282"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p><p class="facitem"><strong>John Swartzberg, <i>Professor Emeritus</i>. </strong></p><p class="facitem"><strong>S. Leonard Syme, <i>Professor Emeritus</i>. </strong>Social epidemiology, community interventions.<br/><a href="http://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/node/15518"target="_blank">Research Profile</a></p>]]>
</faculty>
</courseleaf>

