<?xml version="1.0"?>
<courseleaf>



<text>
<![CDATA[  

  
]]>
</text>
<abouttheprogramtext>
<![CDATA[
<h3>Minor</h3>
<p>Human rights have become the moral language of today, the idiom in which we discuss our common humanity and weigh competing claims for resources, rights and protections. The Human Rights Interdisciplinary (HRI) minor at UC Berkeley allows students to shape their education around coursework which investigates the legal, political, historical, economic, social, psychological, and representational dynamics of human rights.</p>
<p><span>Helping undergraduates explore issues via multiple forms of thought and media of expression—through literature as well as politics, journalism as well as law, film as well as anthropology—the HRI minor emphasizes the many different intellectual spaces in which human rights questions are currently being posed.</span><span> In so doing, it encourages students to recognize how human rights are intertwined with fields as disparate as postcolonial literature and medical ethics, as well as with the more familiar fields of political science and international law.</span></p>
<h3><span>Declaring the Minor</span></h3>
<p>The first step in declaring the HRI minor is to fill out an <a href="http://hri.ugis.berkeley.edu/content/hri-forms" target="_blank">Intent to Declare HRI Minor form</a>
 and to meet with an <a href="http://hrp.berkeley.edu/people/hri-minor-faculty-advisors" target="_blank">HRI Minor faculty adviser </a>
to get the form approved.</p>

<p><span>The department encourages students to meet with an HRI minor faculty adviser early in their academic careers. Advisers will help craft a plan of study, approve elective courses, and help students connect with the faculty members whose work best fits their academic interests.</span></p>
]]>
</abouttheprogramtext>
<minorrequirementstext>
<![CDATA[
<p>Students who have a strong interest in an area of study outside their major often decide to complete a minor program. These programs have set requirements and are noted officially on the transcript in the memoranda section, but they are not noted on diplomas.</p>
<h3>General Guidelines</h3>
<ol>
	<li>All courses taken to fulfill the minor requirements below must be taken for graded credit.</li>
	<li>A minimum of three of the upper division courses taken to fulfill the minor requirements must be completed at UC Berkeley.</li>
	<li>A minimum grade point average (GPA) of 2.0 is required for courses used to fulfill the minor requirements.</li>
	<li>Courses used to fulfill the minor requirements may be applied toward the Seven-Course Breadth requirement, for Letters &amp; Science students.</li>
	<li>No more than one upper division course may be used to simultaneously fulfill requirements for a student's major and minor programs.</li>
	<li>All minor requirements must be completed prior to the last day of finals during the semester in which you plan to graduate. If you cannot finish all courses required for the minor by that time, please see a College of Letters &amp; Science adviser.</li>
	<li>All minor requirements must be completed within the unit ceiling. (For further information regarding the unit ceiling, please see the College Requirements tab.)</li>
</ol>
<h3>Requirements</h3>
<table class="sc_courselist" width="100%">
<caption class="hidden noscript">Course List</caption>
<thead><tr class="hidden noscript"><th scope="col">Code</th><th scope="col">Title</th><th scope="col" class="hourscol">Units</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr class="even firstrow"><td class="codecol">HISTORY C187</td><td>The History and Practice of Human Rights</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td colspan="2"><span class="courselistcomment">Select one Social Science Elective (upper division)</span> <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td colspan="2"><span class="courselistcomment">Select one Humanities Elective (upper division)</span> <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td colspan="2"><span class="courselistcomment">Select one Free Elective (upper division)</span> <sup>1</sup></td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td colspan="2"><span class="courselistcomment">“The Human Rights Interdisciplinary Minor Thesis Workshop&quot;</span></td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="odd lastrow"><td class="codecol">UGIS 156</td><td>Human Rights Interdisciplinary Minor Capstone Workshop (and thesis project)</td><td class="hourscol">1,3</td></tr>
</tbody></table>

<table border="0" width="100%" class="sc_footnotes"><tr><td valign="top" class="symcol"><sup>1</sup></td><td class="notecol"><p>HRI Minor electives are posted on the minor website each semester and designated either Humanities or Social Science electives. The Free Elective can be chosen from either the listed Humanities or the listed Social Science electives. See the list of permanent HRI Minor electives below. If you have questions about potential electives, contact one of the minor's advisers.</p></td></tr></table>
<h4>Permanently Approved HRI Minor Electives </h4>
<p>The courses below may be counted in any semester they are offered. Each semester, the minor posts a list of those permanently approved electives being offered plus any additional courses that have been approved for that semester only. Students should refer to the online listings to determine past course approvals. </p>
<table class="sc_courselist" width="100%">
<caption class="hidden noscript">Course List</caption>
<colgroup><col class="codecol"/><col class="titlecol"/><col align="char" char="." class="hourscol"/></colgroup><thead><tr class="hidden noscript"><th scope="col">Code</th><th scope="col">Title</th><th scope="col" class="hourscol">Units</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr class="even areaheader firstrow"><td colspan="2"><span class="courselistcomment areaheader">Social Sciences</span></td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">AFRICAM 125</td><td>History of the Civil Rights Movement</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">AFRICAM/RELIGST 173AC</td><td>Gandhi and the Civil Rights Movement in America</td><td class="hourscol">3</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">ANTHRO 189A</td><td>Special Topics in Cultural Anthropology/Area (Topics include: Poverty and Rights in the Asian-Pacific AND Poverty, Culture, and Rights)</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">HISTORY C139C/AMERSTD 139AC</td><td>Civil Rights and Social Movements in U.S. History</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">ISF 100E</td><td>The Globalization of Rights, Values, and Laws in the 21st Century</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">LEGALST 154</td><td>Human Rights, Research &amp; Practice</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">PACS 126</td><td>International Human Rights</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">PACS 127</td><td>Human Rights and Global Politics</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">PACS 128AC</td><td>Human Rights and American Cultures</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">POL SCI 123S</td><td>Special Topics in International Relations (Gender and International Human Rights)</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">POL SCI 124C</td><td>Ethics and Justice in International Affairs</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">POL SCI 191</td><td>Junior Seminar (Topics include: Transitional Justice; Bringing Human Rights Home; and Human Rights, Global Politics and International Law)</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd areaheader"><td colspan="2"><span class="courselistcomment areaheader">Humanities</span></td><td class="hourscol"></td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">ANTHRO 189</td><td>Special Topics in Social/Cultural Anthropology (Mass Violence, Representation, and Justice)</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">COM LIT 155</td><td>The Modern Period (Literature and Human Rights)</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">COM LIT 156</td><td>Fiction and Culture of the Americas (Human Rights and Representation)</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">EA LANG 101</td><td>Catastrophe, Memory, and Narrative: Comparative Responses to Atrocity in the Twentieth Century</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even"><td class="codecol">LEGALST 190</td><td>Seminar on Topics in Law and Society (Law, Rights and Minorities)</td><td class="hourscol">1-4</td></tr>
<tr class="odd"><td class="codecol">RELIGST 190</td><td>Topics in the Study of Religion (The Ethics of Rights, Gender, and Global Justice: East and West)</td><td class="hourscol">4</td></tr>
<tr class="even lastrow"><td class="codecol">SPANISH 135</td><td>Studies in Hispanic Literature (Christianity and the Origins of International Law)</td><td class="hourscol">3</td></tr>
</tbody></table>

]]>
</minorrequirementstext>
<faculty>
<![CDATA[
]]>
</faculty>
</courseleaf>

